American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Rome Office, 1903-1947, undated, Series 4:; (boxes 32-34; 2.9 linear ft.)
  - Records of Staff: Directors and School of Fine Arts Faculty, 1903-1947, undated, 4.1:
    - Gorham Phillips Stevens (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - Platt, Charles A. (Vice President; Acting President; Committee on the School of Fine Arts; President), 1928-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes suggestions for improving the quality of fellows, staffing, studios, housing, salaries, ideas for Mead memorial, proposed curriculum changes, collaborative problem, married fellows, endowment fundraising, problem with fellows sneaking women into Villa Aurelia during the night, announcement of director Hewlett's appointment)
      - Publications (see Library and Publications (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Richardson, W. Symmes (Professor of Fine Arts), 1914-1915, 1925 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes letter expressing Stevens' opinion of the Ward-Thrasher memorial)
      - Rotch Traveling Scholarship, 1915 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (requests for candid opinions of the Rotch Scholarship men)
      - Sanders, Henry A. (Annual Professor of Classical Studies), 1915 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Showerman, Grant (Director, Summer Session), 1928 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Trowbridge, Breck (Acting President; Vice President; Committee on the School of Fine Arts; Chairman, Endowment Committee), 1915-1926 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence about collaborative problem, ideas for revision of curriculum, architecture fellow Victor L. S. Haffner's plan for third year project)
      - Van Buren, Albert W. (Librarian; Professor of Archaeology), 1913-1928 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (mainly correspondence concerning library business)
      - Vitale, Ferruccio (Committee on Landscape Architecture), 1927-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence about fellows)
      - West, Andrew (Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1924 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letter about where funds might be found to hire Showerman as permanent Professor in Charge of the School of Classical Studies)
      - Wilkins, H. Blakiston (Executive Secretary, Rome), 1920-1921 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence concerning budget, Wilkins' resignation)
    - James Monroe Hewlett (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - General Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Academic Council Minutes, 1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Aldrich, Chester H. (Committee on the School of Fine Arts), 1933-1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence about extending fellowship time for Nelson and Chabanne, collaborative problem, exhibitions, fellows)
      - Boring, William A. (Treasurer), 1933 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1933 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letters about exchange rate, possible reduction in the number of fellows in the coming year)
      - Del Frate, Gastone (Legal Counsel), 1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence concerning possible dispute over proposed building plans of neighboring Siro Maronita College)
      - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1933-1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letters about budget, expense reduction, fellows' activities, repairs and alterations to Villa Aurelia, film of Mussolini's visit to the academy, exhibitions)
      - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary), 1933-1934 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence concerning financial, educational and social problems observed by Hewlett during his first year as director; proposed bequest of a collection of artifacts)
      - McClellan, George B. (Acting President), 1933 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letter about Hewlett's moving expenses and debt to academy)
      - Platt, Charles A. (President), 1933 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence regarding donations to Vitale memorial fund, reduction of expenses by closing Villa Aurelia and moving the director to Villa Bellacci)
      - Pope, John Russell (President), 1933-1935 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence about expense reduction, relation of fellows to Director and to one another, fellows' work and progress)
    - Chester H. Aldrich (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Committee on the School of Classical Studies (James C. Egbert, Chairman), 1936-1938 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Committee on the School of Fine Arts (James Kellum Smith, Chairman), undated, 1935-1937 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes letters about work of the fellows)
      - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1935-1940 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - McClellan, George B. (Vice President), 1937-1939 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letters about fellows, property, library)
      - Pope, John Russell (President), 1935-1937 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes letters about overspending on studio upkeep, library, activities of staff and fellows, budget, Italian income tax, problems with neighboring Siro MaronitaCollege's building plans, concerts at Villa Aurelia, married fellows, funeral of Mrs. Mead, exhibitions, visitors)
      - Smith, James Kellum (President), 1937-1940 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letters about staff and student activities, library, condition of buildings and grounds, travels, evaluation of fellows, finances and expense reduction, Department of Music, exhibitions, visitors, suicide of Librarian Schnacke, staffing, collaborative problem, recommendations of the Committee on the Welfare of Women Students, budget, political conditions, staff housing, arrangements for students to return to the U.S., suggestions for staffing and work that should continue during wartime)
    - Aldrich, Amey, General Correspondence, 1941 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
    - Charles R. Morey (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1945-1946 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence about wages of Academy servants, expenses)
      - Library, 1945 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Smith, James Kellum (President), 1945-1946 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letter about salaries, boarding discharged soldiers at the Academy, opinion about selling Villa Aurelia)
    - Laurance P. Roberts (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - General Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Brown, Frank E. (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (letter of welcome, correspondence concerning housing)
      - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence concerning work on buildings and grounds)
      - Fulbright Bill, 1947-1948 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence expressing hopes that the Academy will be considered for participation in the program)
      - Hammond, Mason (Trustee), 1946 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Howe, George (Architect in Residence), 1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence concerning his appointment)
      - Lord, Milton E., 1946-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence regarding appointment of a librarian)
      - Mendell, Clarence (Committee on the School of Classical Studies), undated, 1946-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (correspondence about staffing, publications)
      - Moore, Lamont (Assistant Director), 1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes letter of appointment, report on activities of fellows and staff)
      - Morey, Charles R., (Acting Director, Rome), 1946-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence regarding arrival of Laurance Roberts, housing)
      - Smith, James Kellum (President), 1946-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5798-5799)
        (includes correspondence concerning Roberts' appointment, negotiations with candidate for position of librarian, staffing, buildings, library, fellowships, housing)
      - Stuart, Meriwether (Executive Secretary), 1946 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
        (request to help exiled sculptor Ivan Mestrovich)
      - Villa Aurelia, 1945-1947 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
        (includes correspondence regarding alterations and their estimated costs)
      - Williams, Mary T. (Executive Secretary), 1947 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
        (letter about housing, fellowships, visitors to the academy, plans to hold a reception for embassy officers)
    - Frank P. Fairbanks (Professor of Fine Arts), Correspondence, 1923-1930 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
      (includes letters about collaborative problem, shipment of student work, studio equipment, fellow Walker Hancock's need to accept commissions in order to aid his mother financially or sacrifice his fellowship to return home)
    - Felix Lamond (Professor of Music) (Box 33, Reel 5799)
      - Correspondence, 1922-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
        (includes letter outlining the history and accomplishments of the Department of Music, correspondence about plans to establish an alumni music colony in Europe, library needs, suggestions for music jurors)
      - Endowment Campaign--Fundraising Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
      - Endowment Campaign--Horatio Parker Fund, 1920 (Box 33, Reel 5799)
        (includes mailing lists, lists of donors and honorary committee members; correspondence regarding raising an endowment for the Department of Music and a fellowship in memory of Horatio Parker)
  - Personal Papers of Director Gorham Phillips Stevens, 1912-1931, undated, 4.2:
    The personal papers of director Gorham Phillips Stevens were also preserved by the Rome office. They consist of correspondence with relatives and friends, financial records, and correspondence and printed matter of various charitable organizations in which Stevens actively participated or had interest. General correspondence includes correspondence regarding personal business, invitations, thank you notes, holiday and get well wishes, letters of introduction, condolences on the death of his mother, honorary degree from Harvard, family news, and congratulations on his book about the Erectheum.
    - General Correspondence, undated, 1912-1932 (Box 34, Reel 5799)
    - Legal Correspondence and Wills, 1922-1931 (Box 34, Reel 5799)
      (mainly relating to the estate of his aunt Harriet S. Cabot)
    - Financial Records, Banking, 1912-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5799-5800)
      (includes Italian banks and State Street Trust Co., Boston; also, bank and fund pamphlets)
    - Financial Records, Insurance (Frank Arthur), 1920-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
      (correspondence, policies)
    - Financial Records, Investments, 1914-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
      (mainly correspondence with stockbrokers Jackson & Curtis)
    - Financial Records, Purchases, 1914-1927 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
      (correspondence, invoices)
    - Financial Records, Travel Expenses, 1923-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, American Red Cross, Correspondence, undated, 1917-1922 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, American Red Cross, Financial Records, 1918-1919, undated (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, American Red Cross, Notes, undated, 1918 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, American Red Cross, Printed Matter, undated, 1917-1918 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Archaeological Organizations (A-Z), 1912-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Architectural Organizations (A-Z), 1913-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Arts Organizations (A-Z), 1915-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Canada, 1925 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, England, 1916-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Greece, 1925-1920 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Italy, Anglo-American Nursing Home, undated, 1914-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Italy, Italian War Relief Fund of America, undated, 1917-1922 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Italy, Keats-Shelley Memorial Association, undated, 1915-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Italy, St. Paul's American Protestant Episcopal Church in Rome, undated, 1913-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Italy, Other Organizations (A-Z), 1920-1928 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Switzerland, 1923 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, United States (A-Z), 1915-1929 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Charitable Activities, Miscellaneous Organizations, Schools, Universities, and Libraries (A-Z), 1913-1927 (Box 34, Reel 5800)
    - Miscellaneous, Menus, undated, 1918 (Box 34, Reel 5800)